Guide to the David Mates Papers ALBA.279
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
David Mates Papers
1972-2006
1972-1976
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mates, David
Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade
ALBA.279
1 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes
David Mates served as a lieutenant in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade during the Spanish Civil War, and later served as commander of the San Francisco (Bay Area) Post of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB). He also served on the VALB National Board. This collection consists largely of correspondence received by Mates in his capacity as commander of the Bay Area Post.
Historical/Biographical Note
David Mates served as a lieutenant in the Abraham Lincoln brigade during the Spanish Civil War. Born in New York, he was a labor organizer in Detroit before serving in Spain. After the Civil War he lived in Chicago and Detroit, where he was an organizer for the United Electrical Workers and a Communist Party activist. Later in life he lived in Palo Alto, CA, and served as commander of the San Francisco (Bay Area) Post of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB). He also served on the VALB national board. He died in 1977.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists largely of correspondence received by Mates in his capacity as commander of the Bay Area Post of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB). Along with regular mailings from the VALB national office and notices from the Bay Area Post are newsletters and notices from Spanish Civil War veterans in Canada and in Europe. There is also a small amount of personal correspondence from other U.S. veterans, including Steve Nelson, Robert Reed and Sana Goldblatt. One envelope contains a few original photos and reproductions of photos from 1937-38 in Spain.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in collection; provenance is unknown. The accession number 2010.024 is associated with this collection.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Veterans -- United States -- Correspondence.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Bay Area Post; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Mates, David
- Correspondence: Art Landis Books, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence: Don Thayer, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence: Milton Wolff, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence: Miscellaneous, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence: Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence: Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (Bay Area Chapter), 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence: Veterans of the International Brigades (Mackenzie-Papineau Battalion of Canada) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Delgation to China, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Executive Committee: Minutes, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Financial, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Flyers, 1974; undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Madison Committee for a Democratic Spain, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous, 1975; undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- National Board, 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- National Board: Minutes, 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- National Resident Board: Minutes, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Photographs (Spain), undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- U.S. Committee for the Carabanchel 10, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- U.S. Committee for Democratic Spain, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)